

## **Tiago Filipe Sousa Gonçalves**

- Porto, Portugal
- +351 914531059
- ☑ tiago.galves@hotmail.com | tiago.gonalves@gmail.com
- ★ tiago.f.goncalves@inesctec.pt
- ★ https://tiagofilipesousagoncalves.github.io
- in https://www.linkedin.com/in/tiagofilipegoncalves/
- https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4744-9174

I received my MSc in Bioengineering (Biomedical Engineering) from Faculdade de Engenharia da Universidade do Porto (FEUP) in 2019. Currently, I am a PhD Candidate in Electrical and Computer Engineering at FEUP and a research assistant at the Centre for Telecommunications and Multimedia of INESC TEC with the Visual Computing & Machine Intelligence (VCMI) Research Group. My research interests include machine learning, explainable artificial intelligence (in-model approaches), computer vision, medical decision support systems, and machine learning deployment.

Besides working, I enjoy practising Karate-Do Shotokai or reading about life, philosophy, economy, politics or fundamental science. Moreover, I do not refuse a good TV series or a good film (preferably at the cinema).

### Experience

2023 - Present

### Visiting PhD Student

Athinoula A. Martinos Center for Biomedical Imaging | Massachusetts General Hospital

 Visiting PhD student with The Quantitative Translational Imaging in Medicine Lab (QTIM), under the supervision of Albert Kim and Christopher Bridge

### 2021 - Present

## **Invited Teaching Assistant**

Faculty of Engineering | University of Porto

- Invited Teaching Assistant during the 1st Semester of 2022-2023 on the course PRO -Programming (L.EEC004)
- Invited Teaching Assistant during the 1st Semester of 2021-2022 on the course TAIA Advanced Topics on Artificial Intelligence

### 2020 – Present

### Research Assistant

INESC TEC | Centre for Telecommunications and Multimedia

### 2019 - 2020

### Research Assistant

Faculty of Engineering | University of Porto

### 2018 - 2018

#### Junior Researcher

Fraunhofer Portugal AICOS

#### Education

#### 2020 – Present

### Doctor of Philosophy Electrical and Computer Engineering

Faculty of Engineering | University of Porto

• Thesis Title: "Interpretable Machine Learning and its Application to Medical Decision Support Systems"

### 2016 - 2019

### Bachelor of Science & Master of Science Bioengineering – Biomedical Engineering

Faculty of Engineering | University of Porto

• Thesis Title: "Deep Aesthetic Assessment of Breast Cancer Surgery Outcomes"

### 2013 - 2016 Bachelor of Science

## Bioengineering - Biomedical Engineering

Faculty of Biotechnology | Universidade Católica Portuguesa

#### **Awards**

#### 2021 MICCAI Hackathon 2021 Best Contribution Award

 Member of the winning team "HIT" (Helena Montenegro, Isabel Rio-Torto, João Nunes and Tiago Gonçalves) with the work titled "Show Me Consistency! Increasing the quality and consistency of annotations"

### 2021 2nd Place World Data League

 Member of the team "Tech Moguls" (Joana Morgado, Paulo Maia, Tiago Gonçalves and Tomé Albuquerque) that achieved 2nd place at the World Data League competition on data science

#### **Extracurricular Activities**

#### 2023 - Present

# INvicta school of VIsion, Computational intelligence, and patTern Analysis (INVICTA) Spring School 2024

• Member of the Organising Committee

## 2021 - 2022 VISion Understanding and Machine intelligence (VISUM) Summer School 2022

- · Leader of the Project Committee
- Member of the Organising Committee

## 2021 - 2022 2<sup>nd</sup> Workshop on Explainable & Interpretable Artificial Intelligence for Biometrics at WACV 2022

- · Member of the Organising Committee
- · Sponsorship Co-chair

## 2020 - 2021 VISion Understanding and Machine intelligence (VISUM) Summer School 2021

- · Member of the Organising Committee
- · Member of the Project Committee

## 2020 – 2021 1st Workshop on Explainable & Interpretable Artificial Intelligence for Biometrics at WACV 2021

- · Member of the Organising Committee
- · Sponsorship Co-chair

## 2019 - 2020 VISion Understanding and Machine intelligence (VISUM) Summer School 2020

• Member of the Organising Committee

## 2020 – 2021 Conselho Nacional de Debates Universitários (Portuguese Universities Debating Council)

• Treasurer of the Board of Directors

# 2019 – 2021 Sociedade de Debates da Universidade do Porto (University of Porto Debate Society)

- · President of the Audit Committee
- · Treasurer of the Board of Directors

# 2017 - 2019 Associação Nacional de Estudantes de Engenharia Biomédica (Portuguese Biomedical Engineering Students' Association)

- · Treasurer of the Board of Directors
- Founder and Secretary of the General Assembly

### 2017 - Present European Students, Sustainability Auditing (ESSA Project)

· Social Responsibility Student Auditor

### 2017 - 2019 ShARE-UP

- · President of the Board of Directors
- Network Manager of the Energy Network

### 2016 - 2017 **Uniplaces**

- Uniplaces Academy Ambassador Program
- University Partnerships Manager Porto
- · Creative & Social Media Manager Porto

## 2016 – 2018 Núcleo de Estudantes de Bioengenharia FEUP/ICBAS (Bioengineering Student Association FEUP/ICBAS)

• Member of the Communication and Image Department

## 2013 – 2016 Associação de Estudantes da Escola Superior de Biotecnologia (Student's Union of the Faculty of Biotechnology)

- · Treasurer of the Board of Directors
- · Vice-President of the Board of Directors

# 2013 - 2016 Sociedade de Debates da Católica Porto (Católica Porto Debate Society)

- President of the Audit Committee
- Founder and President of the Board of Directors

## 2013 – 2021 Tuna da Universidade Católica Portuguesa – Porto (Academic Band of Universidade Católica Portuguesa – Porto)

- · President of the Audit Committee
- · Vice-President of the General Assembly
- · Vice-President of the Board of Directors
- · Vice-President of the Audit Committee

### 2015 – 2016 Erasmus+ Buddy (Faculty of Biotechnology)

• Member of the Erasmus+ Buddy Committee

## 2013 - 2014 Clube de Investigadores - Escola Superior de Biotecnologia (Researchers Club - Faculty of Biotechnology)

· Project "Bacteria around the City", under the supervision of Professor Célia Manaia

# 2013 – 2016 Programa de Mentorado – Escola Superior de Biotecnologia (Mentorship Programme – Faculty of Biotechnology)

• Mentorship Programme under the supervision of the Alumnus José Carlos Pereira

# 2014 - 2015 Jornadas de Biotecnologia - Escola Superior de Biotecnologia (Journeys of Biotechnology - Faculty of Biotechnology)

- Treasurer of the Organising Committee
- BSc Representative of the Organising Committee

#### Technical Skills

### **Programming Languages**

- Python
- MATLAB
- JavaScript
- C/C++
- HTML
- CSS

### **Programming Frameworks**

- Bootstrap
- Wordpress
- Django

#### **Technologies**

Docker

#### Personal Skills

### Languages Known

- Portuguese: Reading (Native), Writing (Native), Speaking (Native)
- English: Reading (Excellent), Writing (Excellent), Speaking (Excellent)
- French: Reading (Fair), Writing (Fair), Speaking (Fair)
- · Spanish: Reading (Fair), Writing (Fair), Speaking (Fair)

### Publications

## International Conference and Journal Articles

- Ricardo Cruz, Diana Teixeira e Silva, Tiago Gonçalves, Diogo Carneiro, and Jaime S. Cardoso. Two-Stage Framework for Faster Semantic Segmentation. Sensors, 23(6), 2023
- Diana Teixeira e Silva, Ricardo Cruz, Tiago Gonçalves, and Diogo Carneiro. Twostage semantic segmentation in neural networks. In Wolfgang Osten, Dmitry P. Nikolaev, and Jianhong (Jessica) Zhou, editors, Fifteenth International Conference on Machine Vision (ICMV 2022), volume 12701, page 127010G. International Society for Optics and Photonics, SPIE, 2023
- 3. Tiago Gonçalves, Isabel Rio-Torto, Luís F. Teixeira, and Jaime S. Cardoso. A survey on attention mechanisms for medical applications: are we moving toward better algorithms? IEEE Access, 10:98909–98935, 2022
- 4. Pedro C. Neto, Tiago Gonçalves, Marco Huber, Naser Damer, Ana F. Sequeira, and Jaime S. Cardoso. Orthomad: Morphing attack detection through orthogonal identity disentanglement. In 2022 International Conference of the Biometrics Special Interest Group (BIOSIG), pages 1–5, 2022
- 5. Ana F Sequeira, Tiago Gonçalves, Wilson Silva, João Ribeiro Pinto, and Jaime S Cardoso. An exploratory study of interpretability for face presentation attack detection. IET Biometrics, 10(4):441-455, 2021
- João Ribeiro Pinto, Tiago Gonçalves, Carolina Pinto, Luís Sanhudo, Joaquim Fonseca, Filipe Gonçalves, Pedro Carvalho, and Jaime S Cardoso. Audiovisual classification of group emotion valence using activity recognition networks. In 2020 IEEE 4th International Conference on Image Processing, Applications and Systems (IPAS), pages 114–119. IEEE, 2020
- 7. Tiago Gonçalves, Wilson Silva, Maria J Cardoso, and Jaime S Cardoso. Deep image segmentation for breast keypoint detection. In Multidisciplinary Digital Publishing Institute Proceedings, volume 54, page 35, 2020
- 8. Sara P Oliveira, João Ribeiro Pinto, Tiago Gonçalves, Rita Canas-Marques, Maria-João Cardoso, Hélder P Oliveira, and Jaime S Cardoso. Weakly-supervised classification of her2 expression in breast cancer haematoxylin and eosin stained slides. Applied Sciences, 10(14):4728, 2020
- 9. Ana F Sequeira, Wilson Silva, João Ribeiro Pinto, Tiago Gonçalves, and Jaime S Cardoso. Interpretable biometrics: Should we rethink how presentation attack detection is evaluated? In 2020 8th International Workshop on Biometrics and Forensics (IWBF), pages 1–6. IEEE, 2020
- 10. Tiago Gonçalves, Wilson Silva, Maria J Cardoso, and Jaime S Cardoso. A novel approach to keypoint detection for the aesthetic evaluation of breast cancer surgery outcomes. Health and Technology, pages 1–13, 2020
- 11. Tiago Gonçalves, Wilson Silva, and Jaime Cardoso. Deep aesthetic assessment of breast cancer surgery outcomes. In Mediterranean Conference on Medical and Biological Engineering and Computing, pages 1967–1983. Springer, 2019